<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Data Aggregation | Chun Ly</title>
    <link>https://astrochun.github.io/tags/data-aggregation/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://astrochun.github.io/tags/data-aggregation/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Data Aggregation</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>MIT License</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 27 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://astrochun.github.io/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>Data Aggregation</title>
      <link>https://astrochun.github.io/tags/data-aggregation/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>When the pandemic hit, I used my data analysis and Google Sheet skills to inform</title>
      <link>https://astrochun.github.io/post/covid19_research/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://astrochun.github.io/post/covid19_research/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Without a doubt, COVID-19 has impacted every aspect of life, especially higher
education. Earlier this year, the University of Arizona (UofA)
&lt;a href=&#34;https://view.comms.arizona.edu/?qs=af589cd97cb2617e9fdf2ab657a0d6345f451dbc795ba254bc81195f60626149c14bc1d2f83064236848f4247e26ebfa57a0c9858c2d3201e12beef6136f1cf0df93fc33ec93b71912398904fbc91c6b&#34;&gt;announced&lt;/a&gt;
it would start the Fall 2020 semester in a hybrid mode of in-person and online
instruction, and had prepared for this re-entry in a number of ways.
One of those priorities is testing of students, staff, and faculty to identify
active cases. The UofA was not alone, as many other universities had implemented
their own COVID-19 testing program.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In late August, the UofA provided summary data containing new daily tests
(for the previous day) and cumulative numbers (July 31&amp;ndash;) on their main
&lt;a href=&#34;https://covid19.arizona.edu/updates&#34;&gt;COVID-19 Updates webpage&lt;/a&gt;.  Over time, it
was clear that the numbers were not improving, but I grew frustrated as it was
difficult to see &lt;em&gt;quantitative&lt;/em&gt; trends.  Prior to the start of the semester, it
was said during a COVID-19 webinar that the
&lt;a href=&#34;https://covid19.arizona.edu/dashboard&#34;&gt;COVID-19 dashboard&lt;/a&gt; would be made
available in late August.  So on September 3, I decided to start an independent
volunteer project where I started to aggregate the summary data.  I announced
it on &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/astrochunly/status/1301532415773478912&#34;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, and
started with whatever screenshots I had saved and began putting the information
in a &lt;a href=&#34;https://bit.ly/UArizona_COVID_Testing&#34;&gt;Google Sheet&lt;/a&gt;, which I made &lt;em&gt;publicly&lt;/em&gt;
available for &lt;strong&gt;everyone&lt;/strong&gt; to see. Over time, I had the help of a few UofA colleagues
that connected with me through social media:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jill McCleary, Deputy Director and Acting Head at &lt;a href=&#34;https://artmuseum.arizona.edu/&#34;&gt;UofA Museum of Art&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/ironyofprint&#34;&gt;Cheryl Knott&lt;/a&gt;, Professor in the School of Information&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/scastiello&#34;&gt;Santiago Castiello-Gutiérrez&lt;/a&gt;, Ph.D. candidate in the Higher Education program&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am so thankful to them as this project would not have been possible without them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I chose Google Sheet for many reasons:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Easy to use&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Easy to publish&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Easy to collaborate&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Easy to make charts/graphs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As a programmer, built-in version control&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This project was very much &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Open_science&#34;&gt;#openscience&lt;/a&gt;
as hundreds of users checked out the spreadsheet daily to look at the latest updates.
Since many users viewed it anonymously, it was hard to get exact numbers, but this
was what I found from Twitter, Google, and Bitly tracking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I estimate a total of 545 clicks on either the original Google or Bitly link&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;393 (72%) of those clicks were through Twitter and Facebook&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The spreadsheet was shared via other platforms (SMS, email, etc.) for nearly
152 additional clicks (28%)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There were 146 unique non-anonymous viewers to the Google Sheet&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using Bitly, I was able to see that viewers included those in at least ten
different foreign countries.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This all happened mostly during a nearly two-week period before the COVID-19 dashboard
went live on September 16.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The source of information came from my colleagues,
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/c/universityofarizona&#34;&gt;UofA&#39;s weekly re-entry broadcasting&lt;/a&gt;,
and using the &lt;a href=&#34;https://archive.org/web/&#34;&gt;WayBackMachine&lt;/a&gt; to go back and look at the
websites. After all the data were aggregated, there was a lot of quality control as some
numbers disagreed, and that needed to be recorded in the Google Sheet with
in-cell comments and source identification.  This is what we call good
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Data_management&#34;&gt;data management&lt;/a&gt; practice.
A preview of the machine-readable consolidated spreadsheet is available below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe src=&#34;https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/e/2PACX-1vQ3asdKKUNbQj9tpMo8dircaSVxDHJR0fKo8L9cLQ3TMqHb-KBzHmCT_iRl2ie6xbtHEV3V5EHZjuo-/pubhtml?gid=880188181&amp;single=true&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; width=&#34;715&#34; height=&#34;450&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, after I felt confident of all the numbers, &lt;a href=&#34;featured.png&#34;&gt;I put together graphs that summarized the testing data.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The final culmination of this hard work by my colleagues and I is publishing
the final table and visualization in the
&lt;a href=&#34;https://arizona.figshare.com&#34;&gt;UofA Research Data Repository&lt;/a&gt;. The work is titled
&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.25422/azu.data.12966581&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Independent Data Aggregation, Quality Control and Visualization of University of Arizona COVID-19 Re-Entry Testing Data&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; and is made available
under a &lt;a href=&#34;https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/deed.en&#34;&gt;Creative Commons Zero (CC0)&lt;/a&gt;
public domain license:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;&lt;iframe src=&#34;https://widgets.figshare.com/articles/12966581/embed?show_title=true&#34; width=&#34;568&#34; height=&#34;351&#34; allowfullscreen frameborder=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;final-thoughts&#34;&gt;Final Thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I really enjoyed being able to share what I learned with the UofA community.
I found myself needing to make this happen so everyone knew how fast COVID-19
was spreading in the UofA community. We &lt;strong&gt;all&lt;/strong&gt; need to pull together to
fight back, and gathering, checking and illustrating information was the best
way for me to go about it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;#StaySafe, #BearDown, and #MaskUp!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
