<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Open Science | Chun Ly</title>
    <link>https://astrochun.github.io/tags/open-science/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://astrochun.github.io/tags/open-science/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Open Science</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>MIT License</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 27 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://astrochun.github.io/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>Open Science</title>
      <link>https://astrochun.github.io/tags/open-science/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>When the pandemic hit, I used my data analysis and Google Sheet skills to inform</title>
      <link>https://astrochun.github.io/post/covid19_research/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://astrochun.github.io/post/covid19_research/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Without a doubt, COVID-19 has impacted every aspect of life, especially higher
education. Earlier this year, the University of Arizona (UofA)
&lt;a href=&#34;https://view.comms.arizona.edu/?qs=af589cd97cb2617e9fdf2ab657a0d6345f451dbc795ba254bc81195f60626149c14bc1d2f83064236848f4247e26ebfa57a0c9858c2d3201e12beef6136f1cf0df93fc33ec93b71912398904fbc91c6b&#34;&gt;announced&lt;/a&gt;
it would start the Fall 2020 semester in a hybrid mode of in-person and online
instruction, and had prepared for this re-entry in a number of ways.
One of those priorities is testing of students, staff, and faculty to identify
active cases. The UofA was not alone, as many other universities had implemented
their own COVID-19 testing program.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In late August, the UofA provided summary data containing new daily tests
(for the previous day) and cumulative numbers (July 31&amp;ndash;) on their main
&lt;a href=&#34;https://covid19.arizona.edu/updates&#34;&gt;COVID-19 Updates webpage&lt;/a&gt;.  Over time, it
was clear that the numbers were not improving, but I grew frustrated as it was
difficult to see &lt;em&gt;quantitative&lt;/em&gt; trends.  Prior to the start of the semester, it
was said during a COVID-19 webinar that the
&lt;a href=&#34;https://covid19.arizona.edu/dashboard&#34;&gt;COVID-19 dashboard&lt;/a&gt; would be made
available in late August.  So on September 3, I decided to start an independent
volunteer project where I started to aggregate the summary data.  I announced
it on &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/astrochunly/status/1301532415773478912&#34;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, and
started with whatever screenshots I had saved and began putting the information
in a &lt;a href=&#34;https://bit.ly/UArizona_COVID_Testing&#34;&gt;Google Sheet&lt;/a&gt;, which I made &lt;em&gt;publicly&lt;/em&gt;
available for &lt;strong&gt;everyone&lt;/strong&gt; to see. Over time, I had the help of a few UofA colleagues
that connected with me through social media:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jill McCleary, Deputy Director and Acting Head at &lt;a href=&#34;https://artmuseum.arizona.edu/&#34;&gt;UofA Museum of Art&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/ironyofprint&#34;&gt;Cheryl Knott&lt;/a&gt;, Professor in the School of Information&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/scastiello&#34;&gt;Santiago Castiello-Gutiérrez&lt;/a&gt;, Ph.D. candidate in the Higher Education program&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am so thankful to them as this project would not have been possible without them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I chose Google Sheet for many reasons:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Easy to use&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Easy to publish&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Easy to collaborate&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Easy to make charts/graphs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As a programmer, built-in version control&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This project was very much &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Open_science&#34;&gt;#openscience&lt;/a&gt;
as hundreds of users checked out the spreadsheet daily to look at the latest updates.
Since many users viewed it anonymously, it was hard to get exact numbers, but this
was what I found from Twitter, Google, and Bitly tracking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I estimate a total of 545 clicks on either the original Google or Bitly link&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;393 (72%) of those clicks were through Twitter and Facebook&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The spreadsheet was shared via other platforms (SMS, email, etc.) for nearly
152 additional clicks (28%)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There were 146 unique non-anonymous viewers to the Google Sheet&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using Bitly, I was able to see that viewers included those in at least ten
different foreign countries.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This all happened mostly during a nearly two-week period before the COVID-19 dashboard
went live on September 16.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The source of information came from my colleagues,
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/c/universityofarizona&#34;&gt;UofA&#39;s weekly re-entry broadcasting&lt;/a&gt;,
and using the &lt;a href=&#34;https://archive.org/web/&#34;&gt;WayBackMachine&lt;/a&gt; to go back and look at the
websites. After all the data were aggregated, there was a lot of quality control as some
numbers disagreed, and that needed to be recorded in the Google Sheet with
in-cell comments and source identification.  This is what we call good
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Data_management&#34;&gt;data management&lt;/a&gt; practice. Then, after
I felt confident of all the numbers, I put together graphs that summarized the
testing data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The final culmination of this hard work by my colleagues and I is publishing
the final table and visualization in the
&lt;a href=&#34;https://arizona.figshare.com&#34;&gt;UofA Research Data Repository&lt;/a&gt;. The work is titled
&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.25422/azu.data.12966581&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Independent Data Aggregation, Quality Control and Visualization of University of Arizona COVID-19 Re-Entry Testing Data&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; and is made available
under a &lt;a href=&#34;https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/deed.en&#34;&gt;Creative Commons Zero (CC0)&lt;/a&gt;
public domain license:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&#34;https://widgets.figshare.com/articles/12966581/embed?show_title=true&#34; width=&#34;568&#34; height=&#34;351&#34; allowfullscreen frameborder=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;final-thoughts&#34;&gt;Final Thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I really enjoyed being able to share what I learned with the UofA community.
I found myself needing to make this happen so everyone knew how fast COVID-19
was spreading in the UofA community. We &lt;strong&gt;all&lt;/strong&gt; need to pull together to
fight back, and gathering, checking and illustrating information was the best
way for me to go about it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;#StaySafe, #BearDown, and #MaskUp!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UofA Research Data Repository</title>
      <link>https://astrochun.github.io/project/redata/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://astrochun.github.io/project/redata/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;overview&#34;&gt;Overview&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There has been a growing needs for data publishing and digital preservation to
enable open and reproducible science.  One of the major drivers for researchers
is the requirement from federal agencies (e.g., NSF, NASA, NIH, DoE)
of a &lt;a href=&#34;https://data.library.arizona.edu/data-management-plans&#34;&gt;data management plan&lt;/a&gt;.
Data repositories, such as, &lt;a href=&#34;https://dataverse.org/&#34;&gt;Dataverse&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&#34;https://zenodo.org/&#34;&gt;Zenodo&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;https://figshare.com/&#34;&gt;Figshare&lt;/a&gt; are being
used across all disciplines, including science, humanities, medicine, and
technology to satisfy funder&#39;s requirements and other needs (e.g., publishers
requirements). These repository services focus on following the guiding data
principles of &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.go-fair.org/fair-principles/&#34;&gt;FAIR&lt;/a&gt;
(Findable, Accessible, Interoperable, and Reusable).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to these public repositories, R-1 universities have been providing
institutional data repositories to serve the greater needs of their university.
These repositories also enable university administration to track
research output and productivity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Motivated by a number of factors, the &lt;a href=&#34;https://new.libary.arizona.edu&#34;&gt;University of Arizona Libraries&lt;/a&gt;
is leading the effort to develop and sustain a data repository with funding from the
&lt;a href=&#34;https://provost.arizona.edu/provost-investment-fund&#34;&gt;Provost Investment Fund&lt;/a&gt;.
The repository, called ReDATA, will be hosted through an
&lt;a href=&#34;https://knowledge.figshare.com/institutions&#34;&gt;institutional Figshare&lt;/a&gt; site.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More information about ReDATA is available
&lt;a href=&#34;https://data.library.arizona.edu/services/ua-research-data-repository&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my current role as Research Data Systems Integration Specialist, I:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Develop front- and/or back-end software to enable and automate
identity and access management, data curation, and data preservation,
and deploying them on cloud infrastructure&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Engage with major campus stakeholders to identify and
develop workflows for integrating ReDATA with existing library, campus
computing, and research administration systems, such as, single-sign on
(SSO) with the University&#39;s enterprise-level Shibboleth system,
&lt;a href=&#34;https://orcid.org/&#34;&gt;ORCiD&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;http://hpc.arizona.edu/&#34;&gt;UofA HPC&lt;/a&gt;
infrastructure&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Engage with researchers across campus to use the data
repository for open and reproducible science&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Participate in discussions regarding data repository
policies.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;announcements&#34;&gt;Announcements&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;seeking-aditional-deposits-in-our-closed-beta-phase&#34;&gt;Seeking aditional deposits in our closed beta phase&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[2020-06-01] Access to ReDATA service is currently by request only.
Please contact us at &lt;a href=&#34;data-management@arizona.edu&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;mailto:data-management@arizona.edu&#34;&gt;data-management@arizona.edu&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;service-is-publicly-available-seeking-early-adopters&#34;&gt;Service is publicly available. Seeking Early Adopters&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[2020-03-01] We are looking for early adopters to deposit research
datasets, code, media, and other materials and to provide feedback on process
and policies, while acting as champions for the repository.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’d like to influence how UA’s public research data repository will
operate, we would like to work with you! As an early adopter, you’ll be able
to work directly with the data repository team.  Please contact us at:
&lt;a href=&#34;data-management@arizona.edu&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;mailto:data-management@arizona.edu&#34;&gt;data-management@arizona.edu&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;upcoming-talks-and-events&#34;&gt;Upcoming Talks and Events&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are planning a number of events in 2020.  Events will include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Weekly drop-in for help with depositing data&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This page is under construction. Stay tuned!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tech Talks</title>
      <link>https://astrochun.github.io/project/techtalks/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://astrochun.github.io/project/techtalks/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;overview&#34;&gt;Overview&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Below are materials for recent presentations:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://hackmd.io/NP65F9wUQiCC_kpPFrSivA?view&#34;&gt;Research Bazaar Tucson 2020: Beautiful Technical Documents Easily Made with $\LaTeX$ + Overleaf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://astrochun.github.io/post/overleaf_github_git_sync&#34;&gt;Integrating an Overleaf git repo with your GitHub account (the right way!)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
